<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msDesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Oates.536</title>
                <funder/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Cambridge University Library</publisher>
                <availability xml:id="displayImageRights" status="restricted">
                    <p>Zooming image © Cambridge University Library, All rights reserved.</p>
                </availability>
                <availability xml:id="downloadImageRights" status="restricted">
                    <licence>Images made available for download are licensed under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License (CC BY-NC 3.0)</licence>
                </availability>
                <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
                    <licence>This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
                        3.0 Unported License.</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:id="n1" xml:lang="eng">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Cambridge University</institution>
                        <repository>Cambridge University Library</repository>
                        <idno>Oates.536</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <summary/>
                        <msItem>
                            <title>Sterne's Maria a pathetic story : with an account of her death, at the
                                castle of Valerine</title>
                            <title type="uniform">Works. Selections. 1800</title>
                            <textLang mainLang="eng">English</textLang>
                            <author>Sterne, Laurence 1713-1768</author>
                            <editor role="pbl">pr. for R. Rusted</editor>
                            <editor role="pbl">Betham, printer</editor>
                            <note>The passages concerning 'Maria' from Sterne's Tristram Shandy and
                                Sentimental journey, with a continuation, purporting to be from a MS. in the
                                possession of Sterne's daughter.</note>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc material="paper">
                                <support>Paper</support>
                                <extent>[24]p ; (8vo).</extent>
                            </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origDate calendar="gregorian" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1800">[ca.
                                1800]</origDate>
                            <origPlace>London</origPlace>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <availability status="restricted">
                                <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid
                                    reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref
                                        target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/cgi-bin/eligibility.cgi/">Cambridge
                                        University Library Admissions</ref>).</p>
                            </availability>
                            <note/>
                        </adminInfo>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>
                        <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress
                            Subject Headings</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2012-04-10">
                <persName>CUL</persName>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic decls="#document-thumbnail" rend="portrait"
            url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00001"/>
        <surface xml:id="i1" n="cover">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3430px" width="2160px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00001"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i2" n="cover (inside)">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00002"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i3" n="i">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00003"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i4" n="ii">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00004"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i5" n="1">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00005"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i6" n="2">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00006"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i7" n="3">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00007"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i8" n="4">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00008"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i9" n="5">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00009"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i10" n="6">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00010"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i11" n="7">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00011"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i12" n="8">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00012"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i13" n="9">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00013"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i14" n="10">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00014"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i15" n="11">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00015"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i16" n="12">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00016"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i17" n="13">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00017"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i18" n="14">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00018"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i19" n="15">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00019"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i20" n="16">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00020"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i21" n="17">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00021"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i22" n="18">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00022"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i23" n="19">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00023"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i24" n="20">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00024"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i25" n="21">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00025"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i26" n="22">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00026"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i27" n="23">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00027"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i28" n="24">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00028"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i29" n="25">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00029"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i30" n="26">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00030"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i31" n="back cover (inside)">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00031"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="i32" n="back cover">
            <graphic decls="#downloadImageRights #download" height="3402px" width="2103px" rend="portrait"
                url="PR-OATES-00536-000-00032"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="cover" xml:id="pb-cover" facs="#i1"/>
                <pb n="cover (inside)" xml:id="pb-coverinside" facs="#i2"/>
                <pb n="i" xml:id="pb-i" facs="#i3"/>
                <pb n="ii" xml:id="pb-ii" facs="#i4"/>
                <pb n="1" xml:id="pb-1" facs="#i5"/>
                <note>'Oates.536' written in pencil in top right hand corner of page</note> <p>STERNE's</p> <p>MARIA;</p> <p>A</p> <p>PATHETIC STORY.</p> <p>WITH AN ACCOUNT OF HER DEATH,</p> <p>AT THE</p> <p>CASTLE</p> <p>OF</p> <p>VALERINE.</p> <p> - AND WHO IS POOR MARIA? SAID I.</p> <p>THE LOVE AND PITY OF ALL THE VILLAGES</p> <p>AROUND - SAID THE POSTILLION.</p> <p>LONDON:</p> <p>PRINTED FOR R. RUSTED,</p> <p>13 SHOE-LANE.</p> <p>SIX-PENCE.</p>
                <pb n="2" xml:id="pb-2" facs="#i6"/>
                <note>library stamp reads 'BIBLCANTACAD', number written in pencil '88.4.8509,10'</note> <p>Betham, Printer, Furnival's-Inn-Court, Holborn.</p>
                <pb n="3" xml:id="pb-3" facs="#i7"/>
                <p>STERNE'S MARIA.</p> <p>A PATHETIC STORY.</p> <p>THE Grey-eyed morn had just began to peep thro' the sable clouds, the radiant sun shone majestically oe'r the summit of the neighbouring hills into the fruitful vallies, the blushing rose by its opening buds, with fragrant scents perfumed the ambient air, the silver lily reared its drooping head, the purling rills, in murmuring accents served to heighten the sylvan scene, while the soaring lark, with notes divinely sweet, unfolded the beauties of the creation. All nature was alive and Yorick in high spirits. The convent clock had just proclaimed the hour of four, and the beautiful blue eyed nuns of St. Catharine's were preparing to offer up their morning orisons to their creator, and the cheerful husbandmen were slowly creeping to combat the toils of day.</p> <p>Many are the silent pleasures of the honest peasant; who rises cheerfully to his labour: - look into his dwelling - where the scene of every happiness chiefly lies; - he has the same domestic endearments - as much joy and comfort in his children, and as flattering hopes of their doing well, to enliven his hours and glad his heart, as you could conceive in the most affluent station. - And I make no doubt in general, but if the true account of his joys and sufferings were to be balanced with those of his betters - that the upshot would prove to be little more than this - that the rich man had more meat - but the poor man the better stomach; the one had more luxury - more able physicians to attend and set him to rights; - the other more health and soundness in his bones</p>
                <pb n="4" xml:id="pb-4" facs="#i8"/>
                <p>and less occasion for their help; that after these two articles betwixt them were balanced, - in all other things they stood upon a level: - that the sun shines as warm, - the air blows as fresh, - and the earth breathes as fragrant upon the one as the other: and and they have an equal share in all the beauties and real benefits of nature.</p> <p>Dear sensibility! source inexhausted of all that is precious in our joys, or costly in our sorrows! thou chainest thy martyr down upon the bed of straw - and 'tis thou who liftest him up to Heaven. - eternal fountain of our feelings! - 'tis here I trace thee - and this is thy 'divinity which stirs within me." - not, that in some sad and sickening moments, "my soul shrinks back upon herself, and startles at destruction." - mere pomp of words! - but that I feel some generous joys and generous cares beyond myself - all comes from thee, great - great sensorium of the world: which vibrates if a hair of our heads but fall upon the ground, in the remotest desert of thy creation. - Touched with thee Eugenius draws my curtain when I languish - hears my tale of symptoms, and blames the weather for the disorder of his nerves. Thou givest a portion of it sometimes to the roughest peasant who traverses the bleakest mountains - he finds the lacerated lamb of another's flock - this moment I beheld him leaning against his crook, with piteous inclination looking down upon it! - Oh! had I come one moment sooner! - it bleeds to death - his gentle heart bleeds with it - </p> <p>Peace to thee, generous swain! I see thou walkest off with anguish - but thy joys shall balance it - for happy is thy cottage - and happy is the sharer of it - and happy are the lambs which sport about you.</p> <p>Thus moralizing on the happiness of this life in the midst of a profound reverie, I was alarmed by the arrival of my chaise, the postillion cracking his whip, and chaunting a sacred madrigal to his horses, and the blessed Virgin. Such, my dear Eugenius, is the case in France, I had just settled my cravat, wiped my silk breeches, and compounded with mine host and the little fille de chambre. My father, Mr. Shandy, always did those things with propriety - </p> <note>illegible line of text</note>
                <pb n="5" xml:id="pb-5" facs="#i9"/>
                <p>a thousand congees, et cetera, from this polite nation; that instant, like the swiftening motion of the winged arrow, I darted into my vehicle, and Milord Anglois was off in a trice. - The postillion whistled - and the best road was preferred - there is management. - In this - said I - in journeying through this life, nothing is more pleasing to me than to view the growing crops, conducive to health, abundantly flourish, those were the vineyards, whose salutary effects are so congenial to cherish nature and the heart of man - but woe to the thirsty soul who has no bounds to his appetite. Hail, Temperance, for thou art a cardinal virtue. - Blessed scene, my lips vibrated from my heart. - I had scarcely uttered this before a concord of melodious and sweet sounds assailed my ears. - </p> <p> - They were the sweetest notes I ever heard; and I instantly let down the fore-glass to hear them more distinctly - 'Tis Maria, said the postilion, observing I was listening - Poor Maria, continued he, (leaning his body on one side to let me see her, for he was in a line betwixt us,) is sitting upon a bank, playing her vespers upon a pipe, with her little goat beside her.</p> <p>The young fellow uttered this with an accent and a look so perfectly in tune to a feeling heart, that I instantly made a vow I would give him a four-and-twenty sous piece, when I got to Moulines.</p> <p>And who is poor Maria? said I.</p> <p>The love and pity of all the villages around us, said the postilion - it is but three years ago, and the sun did not shine upon so fair, so quick-witted and amiable a maid; and better fate did Maria deserve, than to have her banns forbid by the intrigues of the curate of the parish, who published them - </p> <p>He was going on, when Maria, who had made a short pause, put the pipe to her mouth, and began the air again - they were the same notes; - yet were ten times sweeter; it is the evening service to the Virgin, said the young man - but who has taught her to play it - or how she came by her pipe, no one knows: we think that Heaven has assisted her in both; for ever since she has been unsettled in her mind, it seems her only consolation - she has never once had the pipe out of her hand, but plays that service upon it almost night</p> <note>illegible line of text</note>
                <pb n="6" xml:id="pb-6" facs="#i10"/>
                <p>The postillion delivered this with so much discretion and natural eloquence, that I could not help decyphering something in his face above his condition, and should have sifted out his history, had not poor Maria's taken such full possession of me.</p> <p>We had got up by this time almost to the bank where Maria was sitting; she was in a thin white jacket, with her hair, all but two tresses, drawn up into a silk net, with a few olive leaves twisted a little fantantically on one side - she was beautiful: and if ever I felt the full force of an honest heart-ach, it was the moment I saw her.</p> <p> - God bless her! poor damsel! above a hundred masses, said the postillion, have been said in the several parish-churches and convents around for her; - but without effect; we have still hopes, as she is sensible for short intervals, that the Virgin will at last restore her to herself; but her parents, who know her best, are hopeless upon that score, and think her senses are lost for ever.</p> <p>As the postillion spoke this, Maria made a cadence so melancholy, so tender, and querulous, that I sprang out of the chaise to help her, and found myself sitting betwixt her and her goat, before I relapsed from my enthusiasm.</p> <p>maria looked wistfully for some time at me, and then at her goat - and then at me - and then at her goat again, and so on, alternately - </p> <p> - Well, Maria, said I softly - what resemblance do you find!</p> <p>I do entreat the candid reader to believe me, it was from the humblest conviction of what a beast man is - that I asked the question; and that I would not have let fallen an unseasonable pleasantry in the venerable presence of Misery, to be entitled to all the wit that ever Rabelais scatter'd - and yet I own my heart smote me, and that I so smarted at the very idea of it, that I swore I would set up for Wisdom, and utter gave sentences the rest of my days - and never - never attempt again to commit mirth with man, woman, or child, the longest day I had to live.</p> <p>As for writing nonsense to them - I believe, there was a reserve - but that I leave to the world.</p> <p>Adieu, Maria! adieu poor helpless damsel! some time, but not now, I may hear thy sorrows from thy</p>
                <pb n="7" xml:id="pb-7" facs="#i11"/>
                <p>own lips - but I was deceived; for that moment she took her pipe, and told me such a tale of woe with it, that I rose up, and with broken and irregular steps, walk'd softly to my chaise.</p> <p>A shoe coming loose from the fore-foot of the thill-horse, at the beginning of the ascent of mount Taurira, the postillion dismounted, twisted the shoe off, and put it in his pocket: as the ascent was of five or six miles, and that horse our main dependance, I made a point of having the shoe fastened on again, as well as he could; but the postilion had thrown away the nails, and the hammer in the chaise-box being of no great use without them, I submitted to go on.</p> <p>He had not mounted half a mile higher, when coming to a flinty piece of road, the poor devil lost a second shoe, and from off his other fore-foot. I then got out of the chaise in good earnest; and seeing a house about a quarter of a mile to the left hand, with a great deal to do, I persuaded the postillion to drive up to it. The look of the house and every thing about it, as we drew nearer, soon reconciled me to the disaster. It was alittle farm-house, surrounded with about twenty acres of vineyard, about as much corn - and close to the house, on one side, was a potagerie of an acre and an half full of every thing which could make plenty in a French peasant's house - and on the other side was a little wood, which furnished where-withal to dress it. It was about eight in the evening when I got to the house - so I left the postillion to manage his point as he could - and for mine, I walked directly into the house.</p> <p>The family consisted of an old grey-headed man and his wife, with five or six sons and sons-in-law, and their several wives, and a joyous genealogy out of them.</p> <p>They were all sitting down to their lentilsoup; a lage wheaten loaf was in the middle of the table; and a flagon of wine at each end of it promised joy through the stages of the repast - 'twas a feast of love.</p> <p>The old man rose up to meet me, and with a respectful cordiality would have me sit down at the table: my heart was set down the moment I entered the room; so I sat down at once like a son of the family; and to invest myself in the character as speedily as I could, I instantly borrowed the old man's knife and taking up</p> <note>illegible line of text</note>
                <pb n="8" xml:id="pb-8" facs="#i12"/>
                <p>the loaf, cut myself a hearty luncheon; and as I did it, I saw a testimony in every eye, not only of an honest welcome, but of a welcome mix'd with thanks that I had not seem'd to doubt it.</p> <p>Was it this: or tell me nature what else it was that made this morsel so sweet - and to what magic I owe it, that the draught I took of their flagon was so delicious with it, that they remain upon my palate to this hour?</p> <p>If the supper was to my taste -t he grace which followed was much more so.</p> <p>When supper was over, the old man gave a knock upon the table with the haft of his knife, to bid them prepare for the dance: the moment the signal was given, the women and girls ran all together into the back apartment to tie up their hair - and the young men to the door to wash their faces, and change their sabots: and in three minutes every soul was ready upon a little esplanade before the house to begin - The old man and his wife came out last, and placing me betwixt them, sat down upon a sopha of turf by the door.</p> <p>The old man had some fifty years ago been no mean performer upon the vielle - and, at the age he was then of, touched it well enough for the purpose. - His wife sung a little now and then to the tune - then intermitted - and joined her old man again, rs their children and grand-children danced before them.</p> <p>It was not till the middle of the dance, when, for some pauses in the movement wherein they all seem'd to look up, I fancied I could distinguish an elevation of spirit different from that which is the cause or the effect of simple jollity - In a word, I thought I beheld Religion mixing in the dance - but as I had never seen her so engaged, I should have look'd upon it now as one of the illusious of an immagion which is eternally misleading me, had not the old man as soon as the dance ended, said, that this was their constant way: and that all his life long, he made it a rule, after supper was over. to call out his family to dance and rejoice! believing, he said, that a cheerful and contented mind was the best sort of thanks to Heaven that an illiterate peasant to pay. - </p> <p> - Or a learned prelate either, said I.</p> <p>Look into private life - behold how good and pleasant</p>
                <pb n="9" xml:id="pb-9" facs="#i13"/>
                <p>a thing it is to live together in unity; - it is like the precious ointment poured upon the head of Aaron, that run down to his skirts; importing that this balm of life is felt and enjoyed, not only by governors of kingdoms, but is derived down to the lowest rank of life, and tasted in the most private recesses; - all, from the king to the peasant, are refreshed with its blessings, without which we can find no comfort in any thing this world can give. - It is this blessing gives every one to sit quietly under his vine, and reap the fruits of his labour and industry: - in one word, which bespeaks who is the bestower of it - it is that only which keeps up the harmony and order of the world, and preserves every thing in it from ruin and confusion.</p> <p>I never felt what the distress of plenty was in any one shape till now - to travel it through the Bourbonnois, the sweetest part of France - in the hey-day of the vintage, when Nature is pouring her abundance into every one's lap, and every eye is lifted up - a journey through each step of which Music beats time to Labour, and all her children are rejoicing as they carry in their clusters - to pass through this with my affections flying out, and kindling at every group before me - and every one of them was pregnant with adventures.</p> <p>Just Heaven! - it would fill up twenty volumes - and alas! I have but a few small pages of this to crowd it into - and half these must be taken up with the poor Maria my friend Mr. Shandy met with near Moulines.</p> <p>The story he had told of that disordered maid affected me not a little in the reading; but when I got within the neighbourhood where she lived, it returned so strong into my mind, that I could not resist an impulse which promoted me to go half a league out of the road, to the village where her father dwelt, to inquire after her.</p> <p>'Tis going, I own, like the Knight of the Woeful Countenance, in quest of melancholy adventures - but I know not how it is, but I am never so perfectly conscious of the existence of a soul within me, as when I am entangled in them.</p> <p>The old mother came to the door; her looks told me the story before she opened her mouth. - She had</p>
                <pb n="10" xml:id="pb-10" facs="#i14"/>
                <p>lost her husband; he had died, she said, of anguish for the loss of Maria's senses, about a month before - She had feared at first, she added, that it would have plundered her poor girl of what understanding was left - but, on the contrary, it had brought her more to herself - still she could not rest - her poor daughter was wandering somewhere about the road - Why does my pulse beat languid as I write this; and what made La Fleur, whose heart seemed only to be tuned to joy, to pass the back of his hand twice across his eyes, as the woman stood and told it? I beckoned to the postillion to turn back into the road - </p> <p>When we had got within half a league of Moulines, at a little opening of the road leading to a thicket, I discovered poor Maria sitting under a poplar - she was sitting with her elbow in her lap, and he head leaning on one side within her hand; - a small brook ran at the foot of the tree.</p> <p>I bid the postillion go on with the chaise to Moulines, and La Fleur to bespeak my supper - and that I would walk after him.</p> <p>She was dressed in white, and much as my friend described her, except that her hair hung loose, which before was twisted within a silk net. - She had superadded likewise to her jacket, a pale green ribband, which fell across her shoulder to the waist; at the end of which hung her pipe. - Her goat had been as faithful as her lover; and she had got a little dog in lieu of him, which she had kept tied by a string to her girdle; as I looked at her dog, she drew him towards her with a string - "Thou should not leave me, Sylvio," said she. I looked in Maria's eyes, and saw she was thinking more of her father than of her lover or her little goat; for, as she uttered them, the tears trickled down her cheeks.</p> <p>I sat down close by her; and Maria let me wipe them away as they fell, with my handkerchief. - I then steeped it in my own - and then in her's - and then in mine - and then I wiped her's again - and as I did it, I felt such undescribable emotions within me, as I am sure could not be accounted for from any combinations of matter and motion.</p> <p>I am positive I have a soul; nor can all the books</p>
                <pb n="11" xml:id="pb-11" facs="#i15"/>
                <p>with which the materialists have pestered the world ever convince me to the contrary.</p> <p>When Maria had come a little to herself, I asked her if she remembered a pale, thin person of a man, who had sat down betwixt her and her goat about two years before? She said, she was unsettled much at that time, but remembered it upon two accounts - that, ill as she was, she saw the person pitied her: and next, that her goat had stolen his handkerchief, and she had beat him for the theft - she had washed it, she said, in the brook, and kept it ever since in her pocket, to restore it to him in case she should ever see him again, which, she added, he had half promised her. As she told me this, she took the handkerchief out of her pocket to let me see it: she had folded it up neatly in a couple of wine leaves, tied round with a tendril. - On opening it, I saw an S marked on one of the corners. She had, since that, she told me, strayed as far as Rome, and walked round St. Peter's once - and returned back - that she found her way alone across the Appennines - had travelled over all Lombardy without money - and through the flinty roads of Savoy without shoes - how she had borne it, and how she had got supported, she could not tell - but God tempers the wind, said Maria, to the shorn Lamb.</p> <p>Shorn, indeed! and to the quick, said I; and wast thou in my own land, where I have a cottage, I would take thee to it, and shelter thee: thou shouldst eat of my own bread, and drink of my own cup - I would be kind to thy Sylvio - in all thy weaknesses and wanderings I would seek after thee, and bring thee back - when the sun went down, I would say my prayers: and when I had done, thou shouldst play thy evening song upon thy pipe, nor would thy incense of my sacrifice be worse accepted for entering Heaven along with that of a broken heart.</p> <p>Nature melted within me, as I uttered this; and Maria observed, as I took out my handkerchief, that it was steeped too much already to be of use, would needs go wash it in the stream - and where will you dry it, Maria? said I - I will dry it in my bosom, said she, - 'twill do me good.</p> <p>And is your heart still so warm, Maria? said I.</p> <p>I touched upon the string on which hung all her sorrows - she looked with wistful disorder for some</p>
                <pb n="12" xml:id="pb-12" facs="#i16"/>
                <p>time in my face; and then, without saying any thing, took her pipe, and played her service to the Virgin - The string I had touched ceased to vibrate - in a moment or two Maria returned to herself - let her pipe fall - and rose up.</p> <p>And where are you going, Maria? said I - She said, to Moulines. - Let us go, said I, together. - Maria put her arm within mine, and lengthening the string, to let the dog follow - in that order we entered Moulines.</p> <p>Though I hate salutations and greetings in the market-place, yet when we got into the middle of this, I stooped to take my last look and farewel of Maria.</p> <p>Maria, though not tall, was nevertheless of the first order of fine forms - affliction had touched her looks with something that was scarce earthly - still she was feminine - and so much was there about her of all that the heart wishes, or the eye looks for in woman, that could the traces be ever worn out of her brain, and those of Eliza's out of mine, she should not only eat of my bread and drink of my cup, but Maria should lie in my bosom, and be unto me as a daughter. Adieu, poor luckless maiden! - imbibe the oil and wine which the compassion of a stranger, as he journeyeth on his way now pours into thy wounds. - The Being who has twice bruised thee, can only bind them up for ever.</p> <p>As the inquisitive reader would wish to know what became of poor Maria, the following is taken from a manuscript in the possession of Mrs. Medalle, daughter of Sterne, and is briefly as follows.</p> <p>Having been met with by a family travelling, it begins thus: - </p> <p>On the fifth day of our journey into Italy, we found ourselves within six hours advance to Valerine Castle. The clouds seemed to indicate an approaching storm; rain fell in large drops, and several claps of thunder were heard at a distance. Matilda was alarmed, and begged they might alight at some place where they might find shelter till the tempest should in some degree abate. - In vain they looked round for a cottage or hovel to answer their purpose; no such place could be seen; when their attention was called off by the sight of a young girl, seemingly about sixteen. - Her hands were clasped, and her eyes lifted towards <note>illegible line of text</note> showed both terror and</p>
                <pb n="13" xml:id="pb-13" facs="#i17"/>
                <p>distress. Leonard drove to the spot where she stood, and Alfred offered the shelter of their vehicle, which she accepted with joy; and, by her thanks for their kindness, they perceived she was a native of France. Matilda enquired to what part she was going. - She answered with an unaffected simplicity, "Anywhere." They were both astonished at the reply, but restrained their curiosity, and desired Leonard to drive on.</p> <p>The storm had now blown over, though the clouds were still gloomy; but they again joined, and seemed to foretel another war of elements. - Vivid flashes of lightning darted on the ground, and loud claps of thunder burst over their heads. - Matilda declared she would not travel while it lasted; and Maria (who had now told us her name) was extremely terrified. At that moment they perceived the turrets of Valerine Castle rise above the trees which surrounded it. Alfred ordered Leonard to drive immediately to it.</p> <p>Matilda shuddered, yet was ashamed to confess her fears. It was now nearly dark, and they entered a grove of ancient cedars, that led to the front gate. The lightning was horrid, and the thunder seemed to shake even the centre of the earth; - both Maria and Matilda were nearly insensible, when the carriage stopped before the castle.</p> <p>Leonard had not quitted the mule he rode on above two minutes, before the animal was struck dead at his feet, and each expected the same fate. - Alfred flew to the gates, and being assisted, they yielded to their strength, and burst open.</p> <p>Leonard drove into the court-yard; having pushed against the heavy folding doors that led to the internal part, they easily opened, but with a noise that confirmed no one had entered this dreary mansion for many years. Maria and Matilda were carried into the hall.</p> <p>Leonard having kindled a fire, the party looked on the gloomy place with horror.</p> <p>Valerine Castle was situated near the gulph of Genoa: its lofty turrets, on one side, commanded a view of Piedmont. The building was in every respect calculated to inspire awe and solemnity. After the death of the Count Maserini, many strange accounts were talked of by the peasants, and Count D'Ollifont's</p>
                <pb n="14" xml:id="pb-14" facs="#i18"/>
                <p>sudden departure from it at the funeral of his uncle, seemed to confirm those reports that had before been circulated through the country. From that time it was shut up, without any of the furniture being removed; and no one had been known to enter it till Signor Maserini, son to the late Count, and father to Alfred and Matilda. His sudden disappearance raised the horror of the place more than ever; even those who had before laughed at the superstition of their neighbours, were extremely alarmed at so dreadful and uncommon an occurrence. No person ever walked beyond the entrance of the grove that led to the castle; and the only human habitation that stood near it, was  a cell which contained an old hermit, who had lived there ever since the castle had been forsaken, and subsisted on the charity of the cottagers. The travellers remained in the hall till day light, when the storm abated, and they began to wish for some repose. Leonard pulled two arm chairs, which stood in a recess, towards the fire, and Maria and Matilda strove to sleep in them; while Alfred and his servant laid themselves down on an old bench that stood near the spot. After some hours they awoke, and found themselves much refreshed. Leonard was dispatched to see that the gates were close to prevent suspicion. They then opened their portmanteau, and found they had provisions for that day: this circumstance was fortunate. They had now an opportunity to take an account of their situation; and Alfred asking his sister if she had any objection to explore with him the apartments, she chearfully consented; but Maria was terrified at the idea of attending them.</p> <p>The castle was ancient and truly noble; the situation of this place, said Alfred, shews that its inhabitants left it on a sudden. They, however, contrived to make up some beds; and, after a night of good repose, they was very much refreshed. Next day, Matilda asked Maria to relate what caused her to be exposed to the storm. "Alas!" said Maria, "I should have related my history before, but I thought you would censure me; but," continued she, with tears in her eyes, "you shall have no reason to reproach me with ingratitude."</p>
                <pb n="15" xml:id="pb-15" facs="#i19"/>
                <p>MARIA's TALE.</p> <p>I was born at Moulines, of honest parents, though poor, who lived by their industry, by cultivating a vineyard of their own, though the produce of which was inconsiderable. My father had served in the wars, and had gathered up a small pittance to purchase it, which, by my mother's honest endeavours, they made shift to enjoy with ease and content. I had three sisters, who were all what the world called beautiful: the eldest was wedded to Count O-, one of the gens-d'armes of France, but was afterwards killed in battle, and she being left a widow, died of a broken heart, he being insolvent. My other sister, shocking to relate, fell a prey to the base arts of a designing villain, who, under pretence of marriage, fell into the snare of lawless love, and pined away with grief; she departed fully sensible of her error, and praying to the Blessed Virgin for intercession, hoping that all the maidens of the village would profit by her misconduct. My third sister was decoyed away to a nunnery, and of whom we never more heard, but suppose she fell a prey to the base machinations of the monks and friars; and as to myself, though in the bloom of life, I have had my share of trouble; to the honour of my parents be it spoken, I have received a virtuous education, but love disappointed - love has caused many a silent tear to drop, but not without pity from those who knew the cause. I was honourably solicited by a young merchant of Marseilles - (Here a flood of tears bedewed the lovely cheeks of poor Maria) - who had solemnly pledged his honour to the holy fathers that he would wed me without delay, as he revered my person to admiration; and if the blessings of happiness was to be procured, he hoped they would be found in the union of two fond hearts. The day for the solemn ceremony was proclaimed to the priest, who read aloud from the rostrum the banns necessary for our intended nuptials twice. But oh! fatal day! for, on the third recital, they were forbid by a neighbouring aged priest, who, I have found, was enamoured of me, and intended to reserve me for himself, for the wicked purposes of seduction. The cruelty of such a proceeding threw me into a deep melancholy, and at last bereft me of my reason. I wandered forlorn, as I have been told, through the</p>
                <pb n="16" xml:id="pb-16" facs="#i20"/>
                <p>villages, with a little goat, playing on a pipe, from which I blew a concord of sweet melodious sounds, whose accents attracted an unknown traveller to the poplar I was sitting under; I then had a little cur attached to my girdle. After conversing some time, he requested me to walk - I cheerfully submitted - the spiritual consolation he gave me pierced the inmost recesses of my soul. We walked to the market-place, where he saluted me with the solemn sacred kiss of peace, and with a heart-felt adieu departed that instant. Blessed be the author of my existence, returning reason re-assumed its wonted seat; the sudden extasy I felt surpasseth all human understanding never to be expressed. I then wandered I knew not where, with Providence for my guide, till my guardian angel threw me into the arms of ye, my worthy protectors.</p> <p>Both Alfred and Matilda thanked Maria for the recital of her narrative: they pitied her misfortunes, and promised to protect her as long as it was in their power. Afrer some conversation, they retired to their apartments. - Maria having lighted a wax taper, they took leave of Alfred for the night. "Before we go to rest," said Matilda, "I will take a survey of this chamber." Maria trembled; Matilda took the taper, and walked round it. The apartment had a gloomy appearance. - The bed had been noble and elegant, but was now decayed, the furniture had been of crimson velvet. An old-fashioned cabinet, which had been ornamented with crimson figures, and stood in a gothic recess, seemed to represent a tomb. Matilda, in vain, strove to open the former; it was locked, nor could she find any key. The wainscotting was hung round with large pictures, but except one, they were all nearly destroyed, so as to make it impossible to discover the subjects. That which was in some preservation was the portrait of a man in an Italian habit. He seemed of middle size and elegant figure, but the countenance was melancholy and dejected, while he rested with one arm on the fragment of a grave-stone. Matilda gazed on it for a considerable time; it was extremely like the miniature of her father, which she wore. She stood in such a situation that the eyes seemed to look full at her. Horrid ideas now arose in her mind: she almost fancied she</p>
                <pb n="17" xml:id="pb-17" facs="#i21"/>
                <p>saw the features move: - the thought overcame her: she shuddered, sunk in a chair, and burst into a flood of tears Maria had observed her, and now joined her tears with those of Matilda; yet strove to give her comfort. Her efforts at last succeeded, and, drying her tears, the former retired to a restless pillow.</p> <p>It was a considerable time before Matilda could close her eyes; the misfortunes appeared more terrible than ever. Maria was in a serene sleep; all was silent: her eyes wandered over the chamber; and she could still see, by the dim light of the wood fire, the face still seemed to look at her. Horrid visions now floated on her brain. Her father approached, covered with blood; and with an angry tone, called on her to revenge his murder. She started, and now dreamed she saw herself in an apartment of the castle that was hung with black, in the middle of which lay a corspe in state; she walked up to the coffin, a voice whispered her, it was her grandfather. His countenance was black, and it struck her he was poisoned. At that moment Count D'Ollifont appeared; he attempted to force her from the spot; but, at the apparition of her father, which then ascended with an ashy paleness, and disfigured with wounds, he fled, and Matilda, in the struggle of horror, again awoke. During the whole night, her mind was disordered, she arose by no means refreshed. The breakfast, which Maria had prepared, was served int he first apartment next the hall. Alfred noticed the pale looks of his sister, and asked, with a smile, if she had been disturbed by any of the ghosts. She declared she had not been in the least alarmed; and each answering in the same manner, their fears partly vanished.</p> <p>They consulted the best method to procure provision, at last it was agreed that Leonard should go and mix with others in the public market, and gain some inteligence concerning their residence, and other circumstances relative to the Count: but Alfred desired him by no means to force the conversation, as it might raise curiosity in the peasantry to know who and what he was. Alfred now proposed to his sister to examine those apartments they had not had time to look. Maria said she now had courage enough to stay in the great hall by herself. Alfred and Matilda ascended the stair-case, and walked through the suite of</p>
                <pb n="18" xml:id="pb-18" facs="#i22"/>
                <p>rooms they had before seen. They then crossed several others larger. These terminated in a passage, arched over in the gothic style. This place was extremely dark, they, however, with difficulty, passed it, and entered, by folded doors, a more spacious apartment than they had yet seen, and more gloomy. It had been hung with black, and from appearance, had contained a corpse that had lain there in state. Several pieces of tapers were still standing in black glasses, but there was now only the remains of a large plume of black feathers. Matilda thought of her dream, and trembled. Alfred seemed at first struck with awe, but presently recovering himself, laughed at his sister, and strove to keep up his own spirits, by rallying Matilda. She entreated him to return: the gloomy horror of this chamber overcame her, and she found herself extremely faint. He placed her on a kind of couch, that had been covered with black, and made several efforts to open the windows: this was however to no purpose; but after some trouble, he pulled down a part of the broken shutters. Matilda in a few minutes recovered, but declared she would proceed no further. - Alfred persuaded her, but she refused. He wished much to see the apartment, which, by his aunt's manuscript, he was informed terminated, as was supposed, the search for his father. But his sister refusing to go any further, they returned to the hall. Maria noticed the dejected looks of Matilda, but did not enquire the cause. Alfred resolved to examine the west tower the following day, and satisfy his curiosity concerning the mystery of that extraordinary chamber. Maria was in better spirits than she had been, and tried every way to comfort her dejected friends. Both felt the kindness of her intention, and acquainted her with most of the circumstances relative to their misfortunes; there were, however, some events they thought proper to conceal. Leonard returned in about two hours, laden with the purchases he had made. He acquainted them that he had been taken no particular notice of. This was pleasing intelligence, and they sat down to dinner with some degree of cheerfulness. But yet there was something in Leonard's countenance, which showed he had been greatly chagrined, and that he had heard more than he chose to communicate. At the latter part of the day he requested to</p>
                <pb n="19" xml:id="pb-19" facs="#i23"/>
                <p>to speak to his master alone. Alfred immediately granted his request. Matilda was a silent spectator of this mysterious behaviour. Maria was extremely alarmed; she was certain, she said, from Leonard's behaviour, that he must have received some dreadful intelligence. Matilda strove to dispel her fears, but was herself much hurt. When they returned to the parlous, Leonard's countenance was still gloomy, while Alfred strove to assume a gaiety. Their supper was a silent meal, each seemed absorbed in melancholy reflections; after some time they retired. Another sleepless night was passed by Matilda, and Maria requested she would take her breakfast. She acquainted Alfred with his sister's indisposition. He was extremely concerned about it. Leonard seemed more cheerful than he had been, but his master still remained gloomy, that showed some distress lay at his heart. Both surveyed Matilda with a scrutinizing eye, and Alfred asked, with a pretended air of indifference, if she had rested as free from disturbance as the night before. She told him she had. - This reply seemed to give him pleasure; and on her returning the question, he also answered in the affirmative. The alteration in his manner continued but a few moments, and as he again relapsed into his former melancholy. He now mentioned his intention of examining the rooms in the west tower, and asked Leonard to accompany him. Matilda said languidly, that she also meant to be of the party; - at which declaration her brother looked very much chagrined; "and," said he, "you had better decline it, you are so much indisposed."</p> <p>She thought it might amuse her, and was certain the walk would be of service. Maria attended, and they opened the large heavy door that showed the winding stone stair-case of the west tower. They found it very disagreeable to ascend, the place having been so long forsaken, that large webs of dust and dirt almost impeded their passage. They at length, however, arrived at the first landing-place, where two apartments appeared, - the one to the right, the other to the left. They entered the former. It was a small square room, lighter than many they had seen in the castle, but entirely clear from furniture; that on the left was of the same size, and contained several implements of war. They again ascended, and found</p>
                <pb n="20" xml:id="pb-20" facs="#i24"/>
                <p>themselves on the second landing. The apartments on this floor were gloomy; that on the right side was where their father had so mysteriously vanished. The furniture was all gothic, and greatly damaged, while the elevated narrow casements, placed at a considerable height from the floor, gave this room a most dreary and solitary appearance; in short, it greatly resembled, and had, they supposed, in former times, been used as a place of confinement for some unfortunate prisoner. Leonard examined the boards, and they could plainly perceive those spots of blood which had been before observed by Edward and the physician. In all probability this blood was their father's! - the idea struck each of them. Maria was greatly shocked and terrified; Leonard conversed with considerable emotion in private with his master for some minutes, while Matilda, unable to bear her own feelings. burst into a flood of tears. Some hours were again spent by Alfred and Leonard in a private conference above. Both still retained a settled melancholy on their features, while Maria was more astonished, and Matilda more alarmed than ever. The reason of her brother's secresy she could by no means discover: their supper was again a silent meal, and they retired without any conversation having passed.</p> <p>Maria was soon in a profound sleep, but Matilda's thoughts on her brother's behaviour robbed her of repose. All was silent again for some time; but after an interval of some minutes, she heard her brother check Leonard for talking so loud; "Matilda," said he, "may not yet be asleep." They then continued so low, that she could not even understand one word. After another interval, Leonard answered to a question which Alfred asked him, that "It was not the time." - "If I die int he attempt," said Alfred, "I will unravel this mystery: - and if I once -" "For heaven's sake," continued Alfred, "follow it to the utmost, but at all events do not discover -" Matilda and Maria having joined them in this mysterious affair. "This is a terrible night," said Leonard, "but I will protect you to the last drop of my blood." - "And so will I," cried Alfred, staggering from his seat; "I will protect you both." - "Talk not of protecting us, Alfred," answered Matilda, "for if the spirit of our father at this time walks in these</p>
                <pb n="21" xml:id="pb-21" facs="#i25"/>
                <p>apartments, it is but to reproach you for your present disgraceful situation. - Come, Maria! we will go to bed." "Oh! no indeed, Mademoiselle! I dare not," said Maria, "I cannot move." Matilda's reproach seemed to have some effect on her brother. "My father!" he exclaimed. A deep groan! "Hark! Hark! he answers me! it is from that room! I'll see him, if I die." Another groan! "Hark again!" he exclaimed, "I will go; by heavens, I will be satisfied." At that moment he disengaged himself from Leonard, who catching up a sword, followed him. They both rushed to the dark part of the room. Alfred was first: - : he pushed open the folding doors. An amazing flash of lightning illumined the apartment they entered. Alfred in a tone of horror, exclaimed, "There!". The object caught Leonard's eye. "In the name of the Holy Virgin," said the old man, "who art thou?" " 'Tis gone, 'tis vanished," answered Alfred. He was right: there was nothing now to be seen. Thus ended an adventure which seemed in a great measure to confirm all the terrific reports concerning Valerine castle.</p> <p>Leonard having discovered an old hermit, whose cave was at the bottom of a long walk of cypress-trees, persuaded Matilda, Alfred, and Maria, to go to him, and learn the paticulars of the horrid mysteries of the castle. "I should wish to see him," said Alfred, "he may give me some information, people say that he can. Matilda having found a manuscript in one of the gloomy apartments, carried with her. It was a small roll of parchment, the language was French; but what were her sensations, when her father's name appeared at the bottom. A sudden faintness seized her, but she was able to peruse it, which ran thus: "Oh, father of mercy! where is thy thunder to crush to the earth those who disgrace they image. I am basely murdered by the Count D'Ollifont. When they went to the hermit, he confirmed it for truth, the count was immediately arrested, who sent for the parties. his eyes turned upon them, a kind of cold shivering seized him, and drops of perspiration appeared on his forehead. During the course of his existence, many were the sighs he had wrung from the unprotected, yet he shewed some remorse of conscience - who could tell his pains, or the inward workings of</p>
                <pb n="22" xml:id="pb-22" facs="#i26"/>
                <p>his soul: his senses failed the moment they appeared: his convulsion returned with double force - he raved on the name of my murdered father; then, spent with exertion, he bit his lips, and blood flowed abundantly from his mouth - his ravings returned again, and by a sudden snatch, disengaged himself from their hold, and with a kind of exultation in his face, which was now partly black, he then plucked his hair from his head, called for a poisonous draught which stood near him, drank it off, and then, with a stifled laugh, sunk lifeless on the ground. Such was the end of this murderous villain.</p> <p>The hermit, who had reason to rejoice at the death of D'Ollifont, now unfolded the mysterious proceedings at the castle. " 'Twas I," said he, "who caused those terrific sensations that you have been witnesses of. Forced by his villainy, I was obligated to take a solemn oath to perform what he dictated, or myself and family must have perished. I was born to a splendid fortune: in my youth I was sent to Madrid to finish my education - 'twas there I got acquainted with this monster. When young, he led me into dissipation, and having spent considerable sums, he persuaded me to turn gambler, the thoughts of which, to me, were horrid. From that moment an universal hatred on his side took place, and the consequence of it was, we never saw each other for years. During that period, he was pracstising the most base arts that the human mind can imagine - I, having arrived to my fortune, lived with ease and content, blest with an only daughter; but being sick of the vanities of the world, I turned hermit. One fatal night, sitting in my hermitage, I heard D'Ollifont's voice mention the name of my daughter. "This night," said he to his servant, a man of infamous character, "must she be secured. You are sure you know the place." - "Oh, replied the other, "let me alone for that, for were the lady's cries as loud as the town bell, nobody can hear her but us. - But why not marry? you might then come in for his fortune." - "Curses on him!" exclaimed the villain, "it is revenge I thirst for, not gain; all I want is, to blast his happiness: I have seen him live in prosperity, while I am doomed to live on a small income - I must work his downfall." I heard no more, but</p>
                <pb n="23" xml:id="pb-23" facs="#i27"/>
                <p>trembled. I unfortunately had a pistol, and immediately advanced and stood before the astonished reptile: he turned pale, and trembled, as did his man, but he lived to invent the most wicked contrivances man ever was guilty of, and to lay to my charge crimes of the blackest dye. 'Twas he caused me to act the phantom, and, by way of revenge, I wrote the manuscript you found.</p> <p>These tragic scenes affected the tender fine feelings of poor Maria, whose delicacy had not forsook her; however, a flood of tears, that trickled down her lovely cheeks, relieved her. When they arrived at the castle, they found the peasantry had been alarmed at the circumstances that had transpired, and many idle stories propagated, but after some months living in retirement, and by the aid of Maria's elegant conversation and accomplishments in music, their castle became the mansion of peace, forgetting, as well as they could, the past horrid transaction. Maria grew every hour more beautiful, if possible, and in the eyes of Alfred quite angelic: her artless charms had got full possession of his heart, unknown to the fair one. But however, one evening when walking with her in the cypress grove, he there unfolded to her his tender tale of love. The surprize of which, and the simplicity of her manners, served only to fan the flame. Pleasure now gave way to pain, and Maria was happy once in her life. The sweetness of her temper, the excellency of her mind, and the simplicity of her manners, aided by her complacency and excellent understanding, made him adore her. Fortune was no impediment to their marriage, virtue was all; jewels and costly apparel were bought, and the day fixed by which Maria was to be made completely happy. The nuptial ceremony was performed by the bishop, the castle was illuminated, and the neighbouring nobility and gentry were invited to partake of the grand festival; friendship, mirth, and happiness, reigned triumphant, the rosy god of wine, Apollo, Venus, and the Graces, were present. Thrice blessed happy day; but oh! fatal - fatal night, (ye gods! how can I express the sorrows of poor Maria) whose delicacy had not been able to support the fatigues of the day, swooned away in the presence of the assembly, but by the help of Dr. - . who was</p>
                <pb n="24" xml:id="pb-24" facs="#i28"/>
                <p>present, she soon recovered. But judge what was the surprise of the visitors, when they found she was missing. How she had stolen away, no one could tell; shocking to relate! Her reason once more had forsook her, and after a long search, was discovered near the hermit's cell, bedecking herself with the wild flowers that grew spontaneously near the spot. maria had selected from the flock a little lamb, (sweet emblem of innocence), to which she was incoherently, though melodiously, chaunting, and seemed completely happy. Her affable disposition soon yielded to persuasion and she entered the castle - but never - no, never to reach the marriage-bed, for the clay cold hand of death had seized her, and she fell a lifeless corpse, in the arms of her affectionate husband and protector.</p> <p>INSCRIPTION</p> <p>ON THE TOMB OF MARIA.</p> <p>Peaceful beneath this marble</p> <p>Rest the mortal remains of</p> <p>MARIA.</p> <p>The new-blown rose</p> <p>Equalled not in beauty</p> <p>Her person;</p> <p>The lily</p> <p>Was but a poor emblem</p> <p>Of the innocence</p> <p>Of her mind.</p> <p>Wanderer, stop! - to her memory</p> <p>Pay the tribute of a tear:</p> <p>Her deeds of charity, of piety,</p> <p>Her sufferings,</p> <p>Would but be sullied</p> <p>Were they related</p> <p>On this cold marble;</p> <p>Long after that shall be decayed,</p> <p>They shall survive</p> <p>In the warm hearts of many;</p> <p>And shall be recorded</p> <p>In that book,</p> <p>From which the hand of time</p> <p>Shall endeavour to erase them</p> <p>IN vain.</p> <note>illegible line of text, library stamp reads 'BIBLCANTACAD'</note>
                <pb n="25" xml:id="pb-25" facs="#i29"/>
                <pb n="26" xml:id="pb-26" facs="#i30"/>
                <pb n="back cover (inside)" xml:id="pb-backcoverinside" facs="#i31"/>
                <pb n="back cover" xml:id="pb-backcover" facs="#i32"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
